Benjamin Luft collection of 9-11 first responders' oral histories
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 1: Oral History Interviews, April 9, 2010 through November 4, 2016
  - Raymond Drach oral history interview conducted by Ashlee McGlone, November 5, 2014, AFC 2015/048: 278
    Ray grew up in the Bronx, on Eagle Avenue. He attended high school in the south Bronx, saying it was a lot of fun with a lot of different nationalities. He has four brothers and one sister and is the baby of the family. Ray worked around automotive equipment all his life and progressed to heavy equipment. Ray moved to White Plains, New York after high school, and the father of a girl he was dating owned a gas station so he started working there. He met his wife after he was self-employed and owned several ‘rigs’. They married in 1972 and they have two children. After working for Penn Central (now called Metro North) for 12 years, he went to the Transit Authority. On September 11th, Ray was a superintendent in the Heavy Equipment Department with the Transit Authority. He was working in the Brooklyn shop when he heard the plane had crashed into the towers. Some people working in the upper yard had seen the crash. All their equipment was assembled at the Atlantic Street yard, and it was a five mile long convoy. They took all the equipment to the Trade Center (cranes, etc.) and it was difficult keeping the convoy together. There were approximately 70 men reporting to the site, and none of them knew what to think; they just knew they had to get there to help. When they finally arrived, it was total chaos. Dump trucks were lining the streets, 40 on each side, it was “hard to believe”. People were walking, covered in dust. They could see desks and file cabinets hanging; it was sad and unexplainable. “We were there to clean up” – they brought front loaders, flat beds, fork lifts, dump trucks. To get into the area they were ordered to crush police cars, unmarked cars, “just get them out of the way.” Ray couldn’t put it all together; he saw boots, scud packs – “Where did they all go? They disintegrated. So, where are they? In Heaven, that’s where.” It started to hit him that there had been bodies in all those boots and scud packs, and he began to cry. Ray went home that night in a transit truck so he could get back in the next day. His wife was panicky, but he went back to work around 5am; he got “just a little break” because we “have to help when we’re needed, gotta do what you gotta do.” That next day there was less chaos, and more control. His job was to make sure all the men were placed in time – who’s coming and going, who’s hurt, “keeping track of everyone”. He had to make sure there was fuel, and that all the equipment was up and running. Where each truck was, where it was going – “then the paperwork starts.” Ray recalls finding a desk ornament, a golf putter, and thinking, “This was on someone’s desk…man, what I am doing on this pile? This is your job, just do it!” He also remembers seeing piles of brand new work boots and socks, so much food: one guy with 15 pizza pies and soda, so many people coming together. “I hope we stay this way for a long time – it was like the sky opened up and rained down all these helpers.” Ray and his men stayed there 5 days until the contractors came. He felt like the contractors were like wolves; “It was greed, money…we’re already here, why do we have to leave?” But once they did leave, they went back to their regular routine. Ray now has prostate cancer, and has no family history of cancer. Ironically, the surgery to remove his prostate was on September 11th, the doctor told him no one ever wants to have surgery on that day. But Ray said, “I’ll take it!” so he will never forget it; he remembers every day and hopes that nothing else comes up. His wife worries, and “looks at me like – are you breathing ok?!” Ray states that he hopes nothing like this ever happens again. He wants everyone to remember that the transit workers were there, “I’m proud of us! Best ride, biggest system in the world!” When asked to make a final statement, Ray says, “Stick together as one, help one another and nothing like this will break us apart.”
    - Moving Images
    - Manuscripts
  - Joseph Pironti oral history interview conducted by Avalon Mason, November 12, 2014, AFC 2015/048: 279
    Joseph Pironti comes from a close Italian family. He has three children and is married to his second wife. He has been an auto mechanic for most of his life and owned a shop for 20 years. On 9/11 he was going through a divorce and was living in a studio apartment in Dix Hills, and his children were young. He was asked to work for an environmental cleaning company because he had the mechanical expertise to maintain the equipment and welding skills needed for the dismantling of the wreckage at Ground Zero. Joseph is no longer able to work because ten years after the attacks, he became ill. He was diagnosed with Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia. He lives his life in chronic pain and the abnormal white blood cells accumulate in his lymph nodes and joints. His wife takes care of him, so it has affected them financially because they cannot work as much. Joseph arrived at Ground Zero a few days after the attacks and stayed in Manhattan in a hotel because he worked 6 days a week/twelve hours a day until January 2002. He described in detail of the whole operation of how the steel columns are broken up and dismantled by cranes and welders, then towed away on a flatbed truck to the barge that brought the debris to Staten Island. Seven huge truck washes were set up to decontaminate the trucks before they drove away with the rubble. Most workers were dressed in a hazmat suits, but he only wore coveralls to power wash the trucks to remove the remaining hot ciders and dust. Joseph also spoke of how respectful the workers were when a body part was found. If it was NYPD or FDNY, an American flag would be draped on the gurney and everyone would take time to pay their last respect. This would occur ten to twenty times a day. Joseph praised the Salvation Army for their wondrous efforts. He said he has so much respect for them now that he never did before. Their volunteers from all over the country were there to serve food, to get clothing or supplies and to just sit and listen to the workers would express their feelings. The Salvation Army also had letters from children from everywhere expressing their gratitude and love for the First Responders, which was especially heart-warming to Joseph. Joseph believes that if the WTC workers had evacuated immediately, we wouldn’t have had so many perish. He also wishes that he had been fitted and worn a respirator, but since he wasn’t working directly on the pile, he was told it wasn’t necessary. Dust was everywhere and was several inches thick. He was able to take hundreds of tasteful pictures that displayed the magnitude of how many structures were affected. He brought them in to share with us and use for documentation if we choose to. Joseph had the opportunity to meet several celebrities and sports stars that visited Ground Zero. He also was served dinner by Rudy Giuliani on Christmas Day, which was posted in the LI Newsday, which he brought in for us to see and keep if we wanted. Joseph now understands why the WWII Veterans were unable to talk about the horrific experiences of war. He feels that Veterans are real heroes because they volunteered to be shot at, whereas, most First Responders were doing their daily job. However, he feels as an American citizen, everyone should volunteer to serve their country. He helped out his neighbors in the aftermath of Super Storm Sandy and his wife was a volunteer EMT. He would do it all over again if needed, even though his efforts left him with a chronic terminal disease.
    - Moving Images
    - Manuscripts
  - James Verdon oral history interview conducted by Ashlee McGlone, November 14, 2014, AFC 2015/048: 280
    James was born in Flushing and currently lives in East Meadow, Long Island. He works for NYC Department of Sanitation. On September 11th, James was assigned to operate the truck called Easy Pack. They started picking up cans with the forks of the truck, and heard a crash – James thought he dropped the container. Then his partner pointed out the smoke and flames. They kept working, and heard a larger explosion – they thought it was time to get the hell out! Cars were abandoned, they saw the Fire and Police departments coming in droves. James remembers with vivid detail the people he saw hanging out of the windows and jumping. No one knew what was going on, no one knew what to do; it was like everything was going in slow motion and people were in shock. They got into their truck, rammed some cars out of the way and got out of there. They drove on roads they normally would be allowed on, and managed to get under the overpasses. The smell of burning metal was very bad, and the smoke was bad. About a week later they were organized to go in, and anyone front loader qualified got called din to run the heavy equipment. They sifted through all the debris in Building 7, which was drug evidence, and then began on building removal. James states it looked like a war zone, but all the people were very friendly and everyone was giving away food. It was depressing for James to be there for his 12 hour shifts; the chaos and feeling of being in a war zone was crazy. No one had masks; when they were finally issued masks with canisters, no one had filter refills. James now has a sinus condition and is a patient at the Mineola clinic of the World Trade Center Monitoring Program where they are trying to figure out his health issues. “I worked at all the ‘places of interest’” – Manhattan, at the landfill, on the pile – “and saw all sorts of guys with equipment – why don’t I have any of that equipment?” James wanted the city to get back to normal and let the terrorists know that they didn’t win. He is proud of the fact that he helped; “I don’t want anything for it, the guys running towards the buildings should get all the credit.” To future generations, James says he hops they are in a lot better state that we are in today. “Seems like religion is always the root of the problems, and I hope they are all past this by then and see how stupid it all is.” He hopes people will remember, there could be peace but he doesn’t see that coming. “I can’t describe the devastation well enough – this was BAD – and it wasn’t that long ago.”
    - Moving Images
    - Manuscripts
  - Michael Blangiforti oral history interview conducted by Avalon Mason, November 17, 2014, AFC 2015/048: 281
    Michael was born in Queens and moved to Long Island after being with the NYPD for one year. He currently lives in Massapequa on the south shore of Long Island, and has been there for 16 years. He is married and has two daughters, ages 12 and 14. Michael worked 20 years with the NYPD, and retired as the Operation Coordinator of the Detective Bureau. He really enjoyed his time with the police department, and when he retired his career path was not over; currently he is the Director of Security for a private security company. On September 11th, he was the Robbery Sergeant in Queens. He heard about the attacks as he was driving with his one year old daughter strapped into her car seat, listening to the traffic report on the radio. The reporter was saying a plane had hit the World Trade Center. There were big changes to the report as he drove from Long Island to New York City. He knew it was a terror attack, and kind of froze – is this real? He was now approaching Queens in a panic, he knew it was going to be one hell of a day. He dropped his daughter to his mother-in-laws house, “Ma, put on the TV I have no idea when I will be home!” Michael’s wife is a CPA and her office was in the WTC. That day she was in training down south; she hadn’t wanted to go to the training because she felt the baby was too young and it was a last minute decision that she would go. She would have been there, and that morning Mike was thinking Oh My God, she would have been at work right now. It was surreal to see the smoke, again thinking, “Is this really happening?!” What was running through his mind was, “OK, you’re NYPD, you have a job to do, go do it.” Once he got to the 110th precinct, the Citiwide radio was on and there was an overwhelming feeling of helplessness. Hearing cops, their brothers and sisters, screaming “10-13, 10-13”, the code for ‘I need immediate help’ – “It felt like we were listening to them take their last breath and there’s nothing we can do to help them.” Then, Mike experienced crushing chest pain and collapsed. They took him to the hospital, but he thought he shouldn’t be there - they would be flooded with patients soon. He was sedated and discharged, and was cleared to go back to work the next day. It still bothers him to this day, no matter how much he talks about it, that he didn’t respond with his men that first day. They worked 12 hour shifts in the landfill and had to create death notifications. He and another detective would have to notify the families that remains had been identified as their loved ones. He will never forget the smell; the enormity of the event hit him as he saw the barges come filled with debris and human remains. The dump trucks would empty and backhoes would spread the debris. It was hot and sometimes still on fire, they would have to wait for it to cool off. Mike describes rebar bent in all different directions, dust that was more like thick sandy dirt in the air, and the distress of finding personal belongings. Mike says that cops develop ‘tunnel vision’ to be able to perform their jobs and focus on what they’re doing: raking through the debris looking for human remains, which would be put into a bucket. “Horrible, terrible, I found a piece of scalp: perfectly parted silver hair.” This impacted him, but it was also part of the routine. “My faith in God was shaken. How does God allow something like this to happen?” One day, a dim and dismal day at the landfill, Mike saw a Catholic priest walking towards him out of the corner of his eye. He was handing out little green New Testament Bibles. The priest said, “Would you pray with me?” and Mike thought – here comes this priest out of NOWHERE and says will you pray with me, is this a message? “A reminder that God is still here, to know that He knew what was going on with me, a message specifically to me – Michael, I know what’s going on with you and I’m still here with you.” There were meal tents for the responders to take a break and eat their meals, but Mike remembers thinking, how can I eat in this place? Supply trucks finally came with canister masks, but this was after they had been told the air was fine – “Obviously it was not.” Mike goes on to say that in his opinion, 9/11 is still happening today, “even right here in this clinic” because although so many died at the event, so many are dying subsequently, and so may responders are being diagnosed with aggressive cancers. A friend of his was diagnosed with stage 4 cancer, “I just saw him at a school function and now all of a sudden he has stage 4?! The cancer took him in six months.” Mike has been suffering from PTSD for many years now and has flashbacks and nightmares. NYPD put him on restricted duty and sent him for a psychological evaluation. He says he still feels guilty, feels that he didn’t do enough. But he states there is a tremendous amount of support available to responders if you seek it out. On the heels of this thought, Mike recalls one family he notified of their loved ones death “just collapsed – they KNEW, but this was the confirmation. They wanted to know which piece was found.” Mike says he was in a very dark place and knew he needed help. He thinks it’s funny that he can sit here now, so many years later, and still see “frame by frame” what happened that day. When asked what he would like future generations to take away from the event and his interview, Mike states that the responders were all human beings. Despite the overwhelming event, the first responders did their jobs – they ran to the site as everyone else ran away; remember the human aspect: the courage, resolve, commitment and selflessness. “That we have a job to do and we won’t stop doing it.” Never forget; he feels that history will write it and it will never be forgotten, but he would ask that people take the time to read it not as a history lesson – “pause and reflect, think of the people, the human aspect, the families.”
    - Moving Images
    - Manuscripts
  - James Bruinsma oral history interview conducted by Amanda Mancuso, November 18, 2014, AFC 2015/048: 282
    James is from Ronkonkoma, where he has always lived. When he was growing up, many people in his community were fire or police department. James didn’t have money for college, so he took the NYPD entrance exam and was hire; he became a homicide detective in 1996. James has several children, one of whom is a junior firefighter with a local department. He wants to be a career firefighter. His family history is interesting—very long line of people in service. The week before 9/11, James had been promoted into a special robbery task force. That morning, he was late to work and heard of the first place crash on the radio—from where he was in his car, he could see a little black mark on the tower. He raced to his precinct, where the lieutenant, who had come in early, prevented the officers from rushing down to the WTC, likely saving their lives. Eventually, he reported to help people across the Brooklyn Bridge and ultimately ended up down at the site. He recalls the “dead, disgusting silence” and not knowing where to begin. James got himself on work rosters and kept returning to the site until Saturday, when orders came down and he was sent to the morgue. The PD wanted their detectives doing detective work, not digging on the pile. James remembered being at the landfill and thinking he had found human remains—but they turned out to be raw chicken from Windows on the World. He remembers finding some bones, shoes, and lots of IDS—he never looked at the names on them. He thinks now of hos stupid it was for the responders to stand around eating free food in the middle of a toxic wasteland. James does feel that the higher-ups tried to “make chicken salad out of chicken shit” when finding remains of first responders; he just wanted to make sure they got the respects they were due. James was a robot during that time, and began drinking to excess to cope with PTSD. He was diagnosed with stage 4 Hodgkin’s in June 2010 and went through chemo and radiation, which ruined his thyroid and precipitated the onset of panic attacks. The combination of prescription anti-anxiety meds and alcohol necessitated his entry into rehab, where he was for 30 days. He checked out on 9/11 of 2013. He is currently in cancer remission, but has many friends who have died. James spoke about the ways in which this has affected his family, his thoughts on post-9/11 politics, and more recent events. He does believe there have been positives to come out of it, but that people are generally more concerned about the cost of gas and war than that people are still dying. He hopes people in the future understand the gravity of 9/11.
    - Moving Images
    - Manuscripts
  - John Baner oral history interview conducted by Christina Rodriguez, November 25, 2014, AFC 2015/048: 283
    As a third generation police officer, John was proud to wear the same shield number as his father and grandfather before him. He didn’t plan on becoming a police officer but after taking the exam he left St. John’s University where he was studying computer science. After 7 years as a police officer he got married and currently has a 20 year old son and a 17 year old daughter. John, a Detective Sargent, was at work the morning of 9/11 when he received a call from the Bureau of Manhattan requesting his team and him make it to the 1st Precinct, just past Canal Street, because a plane flew into the World Trade Center. When he turned on the TV he thought “it didn’t look that bad, it must have been a small plane.” His team of eleven piled into three unmarked cars. When they got the 1st Precinct, John asked them to remain in the cars as he checked in. John found the building empty because the meeting location was changed to the south side near Battery Park. When he got back to the cars, he found some members of his team arguing before a distress call came in over the radio. The call was asking for someone to call the Pentagon because there is a second plane and we’re under attack. John was in the lead car, approaching the WTC as they headed to the south side, when they saw swarms of people running away. He looked over the dashboard, up at the building tops, and saw what looked like glitter (windows) and toothpicks (steel beams) followed by a massive a cloud of dust as the building was beginning to collapse. Fortunately, the detectives in the cars following him realized and were already gone. The driver backed up the car trying to escape the cloud before it engulfed the car. Once they were safe, John found out the detectives were arguing earlier over who was going to drive. Someone in the back seat was complaining the driver was too slow and he thought they should switch. They didn’t switch before John came out the 1st Precinct. But John can’t help but think, had the two switched they would have made it much closer to the buildings and things would have worked out drastically different. This was by far the closest he had ever been to being killed even when compared to a shootout he was involved with several years back. He says “it’s odd when you think of all the things that happened that could have changed…all the ‘what ifs.’” John and his team were stationed at St. Luke’s hospital for a while and then they made their way to the pile. He remembers hearing the chips from the fire fighters PASS devices and seeing an unbelievable amount of paper. Everything else was unrecognizable. He compared the bucket brigade to taking a bucket of water out of the ocean, but something needed to be done. John continued to describe the system used at the Fresh Kills landfill. At first there was nothing there, but as government and civilian agencies joined together housing was built, port-a-potties, and supplies arrived. Barges would bring over the debris from lower Manhattan and a crane would fill a dump truck. The dump truck would spread the debris across designated football sized field where 20-30 detectives would search through looking for body parts, personal items, and the black boxes from the planes. After this search a bulldozer would push aside the larger pieces and collect the smaller materials. The smaller materials were brought to a sifter which would remove anything smaller than a softball. These materials were then placed on a conveyer belt and searched through one final time. Out of the eleven detectives John supervised, seven have severe health issues, one of which has passed. He says 9/11 is a distant memory for most but the general public doesn’t realize how sick people really are because of their exposure on 9/11 and in the clean-up. He believes 9/11 woke the nation up from the horrible things going on in other parts of the word but we are going back. He hopes that from his story people can learn from the 9/11 and other events going on around the world to make sure it doesn’t happen again. Also, remember those who died heading to work and going on with their daily lives. It could have been anyone.
    - Moving Images
    - Manuscripts
  - Joseph Ryder oral history interview conducted by Christina Rodriguez, December 1, 2014, AFC 2015/048: 284